Welcome to the lighter side of the
spectrum, a podcast where we explore how
to find
joy, connection and growth while
navigating the challenges of parenting
kids and
teens on the autism spectrum. Remember
that inclusion and hope are key to making
life better for everyone. And that even in
the most challenging moments, there's
always a lighter side. Now here's your
host, David Kaufer.
I'm David and I'm the father of 18 year
old Quinn Moyes, one of whom was diagnosed
on the autism spectrum just before he
turned three. So I've been on this journey
for
a long time and have had a chance to work
with a lot of different people, met a lot
of different people. I've learned a lot of
things over the time. And so the goal of
this podcast is really to try to share
some of the knowledge, alum expertise that
I've gathered in.
before with people, great people like my
guest today, Elizabeth Zylinski.
Elizabeth,
thanks for joining me on one of our first
initial launches of the podcast. you for
having me. I resonate with what you said
about learning so much from the people
along the way. There's a, Elton John song
I love. And there's a line in it that
says, and thank the Lord for the people I
have known. And it's so true about this
process.
that I don't know how people get through
it without a community. that's funny that
you mentioned that because that's one of
the topics I want to talk about today
actually is community and the role that it
plays, especially some of the
opportunities, but also it kind of creates
some challenges. just to give listeners
and viewers just a little bit of
background. Elizabeth was kind enough to
send over
a bio, but I want to give a little bit of
background because she's really, she's
Just being a great person, just really
impressive. So Elizabeth is the founder
and
lead advocate of Virginia based
Commonwealth education group, LLC, a
special
education consulting practice designed to
bring people, bring together, I'm sorry,
collaborative teams in a variety of
educational specialty areas towards the
common
goal of assisting families with their
students' educational planning. Experts in
the
group include advocates, attorneys,
counselors, psychologists, educators,
depending
on the unique.
needs of the client. So that's a mouthful,
what caught my eye initially is that
Elizabeth and I met in a Facebook group
for spellers. so for those who don't know,
spelling is a methodology that's used by
non-speakers, generally pointing at
utilizing either a letterboard or keyboard
typing.
It's in our case, again, was the key to
unlocking communication with our son who
was
unable to communicate for 16 years.
Elizabeth, want to hear about your
experience as
well, but we met in this Facebook group
and Elizabeth talked about how she's an
advocate. for families and has given a lot
of great free advice, but I know that
this is also your business. you know, why
don't we just kind of start with that,
your journey, Elizabeth, in terms of how,
what brought, what?
Right here, know that there's a lot
probably to talk about, Yeah. Well, Evan
was,
Evan's my autistic son. He's almost 19
after the time we're recording this
podcast,
be 19 in two weeks. Right. And he was
diagnosed autistic when he was three, but
he
was diagnosed non-speaking or unreliably
speaking. Gosh, he was barely over two.
mean, of course, back then you didn't get.
the super, early diagnoses that a lot of
families get today, which is great that
families do get that. But he didn't have
communication until he was about 11. We
had, there's a few different modalities
available in the community. They're all
letterboard based communication. We've
done them all. almost did. Yeah, right.
And I
don't want to be too derivative, but it
really was finding the right community
that
makes
one work over another because you need
that collective support as you're going
through this process. And so, you know, we
had a couple of false starts with
different modalities and I had to be
convinced that it would even work, not
because
I might be something of an exception in
that I always, believed that Evan had more
in there. What I didn't believe is whether
we'd ever reach it. And you know, I
always knew.
Yep. Now he, you know, he's not, he
doesn't beat the stereotypical aspects of
autism. He very, affectionate. makes good
eye contact. He, you know, really super
oriented to social cues. He doesn't
necessarily respond to social cues, but he
absolutely understands them. so I just
didn't, I, thought that what he could say
is
what he could say. I didn't know that
there was any other.
any other way to pursue that, we put so
much priority on the spoken word that we
took it at face value. That what he said
was what he meant to say and that what he
didn't say with, you know, maybe he didn't
understand or he didn't, I don't know
what, but I always knew there was more
there and I just didn't know if we'd reach
it. So it took a couple of people kicking
me in the backside saying, just give it a
try, give it a try. And
right from the beginning. I mean, we all
have our, what I call them, our magical
moments, you know, where there's just one
thing that they do or, style. tend to use
the word say as interchangeable with fell
in because it is what he's saying. I just
want to make that clear for anybody
listening because it doesn't mean he's
speaking
it. but he's still saying it. So in any
case,
You know, very early on we had that
magical moment that, and in his case, it
was one
that I not only was absolutely certain was
genuinely him, meaning the person holding
the letter board could not possibly have
known. But the thing that he spoke about
or
wrote about was just very specifically
unique to his personality. it just, you
know,
it just was one of those things that he
just...
I think maybe it was the only time in my
life that I've just dropped on my knees.
And literally, I mean, I'd love to tell a
story if we have time for that. Please do.
No, I think, cause I think, I think it's
important, like you said, because again,
as
you said, you didn't go into this, like
starry, like, know, like, Hey, this is
going
to be it. I mean, again, I was, you know,
I
I became aware of it from a friend who
happened to be friends with JB Hanley.
know,
I mean, I think as parents, right, we, I'm
sure you went through everything you
could think of. I, again, I don't know,
we've never really talked about, know,
some
of the biomedical things, as well as, you
know, our ABA speech, right? There's
anything and everything, right? We've been
there and nothing had seemed to quote
unquote work. Cause again, like you said,
we're so focused on the spoken word.
So yes, and I will say too, I, know, we
didn't pursue bio med quite as much in
our,
I don't want to get off on a tangent, but
in, never had that profound moment where
we saw loss of skills. never saw them
develop. And I hate to say this, but I,
don't
hate to say this. I took that back. I put
a lot, a lot of stock in maternal instinct
and sure.
Possibly paternal too, but never having
been a father to my knowledge. I can't
speak
to that. I just feel like every time I've
known something in my heart and soul about
my children, it's just never been wrong.
you know, thousands of years of evolution
created us to know these things on a level
that we don't necessarily logically think
through. And I just, I know what I really
think happened. I think in his case, it
very much was.
a genetic, you know, he was just created
this way, but I also believe he
experienced
an environmental trigger that his own
genome was less able to be responsive to.
And
I'm choosing my words very carefully
because he is absolutely perfect exactly
the
way he is. I never speak about him in
terms of, you know, any kind of medical
damage
or anything that way. I think that that's
For me personally, I can't speak for
others, for me personally, think it's a
fool's
errand to go down that path because he is
who he is. And he deserves to be loved and
honored and embraced for exactly who he
is. How he became that way is really not
my
question to answer. I think I know, but
you know, I mean, I was born with red
hair.
A lot of people thousands of years ago
thought that was the sign of a witch. And
they weren't necessarily wrong.
point with this, you know, this is just,
it's who he is and that's all. So anyway,
back to the story of that moment. Again,
not to get off on a tangent, but my
parents
passed away seven weeks apart from one
another in... Yeah, thank you. It's dumb.
I
don't recommend it. No, that's was rough.
I don't recommend it. And one of the great
sadnesses for me, my mother was a special
education teacher and my dad was just, you
know, a...
just loved children, loved them, just a
natural, parent. And they passed away in
2011. We found Spelling late 2015. It was
early 2016. And as we were coming to know
this, reality for Evan, one of my great
sadnesses was, my gosh, mom and dad would
have loved this. And if they're watching
from the great beyond, man, they are just
bursting. They're jacked.
Yeah. So we were in Austin, Texas. We had
gone to see Soman Mukhapajee, the founder
of RPM. And we were in a week long
intensive program that she does. And he
had a
half hour session on the second day and he
had what I call a DEF CON one meltdown.
mean, just, I don't want to get into
specifics out of dignity for him, but man,
it
was not great. think we even scared Soman.
And he went out to the driveway of the
home where her office is and got into our
rental car. It sat there and was just
picking and screaming and banging. she
just
kept going. She just kept the board in
front of him. And I, was recording because
everything gets video recorded. And, the
last thing he, she asked him was what's
one
word to describe our time together. And he
spelled hope and what.
Nobody knew at that time was that word
hope was incredibly profound in my family
of
origin. My father worked with cancer
patients and he did a lot of the
communication
strategy, a lot of the public relations.
And in the seventies, the idea of hope
being something that you can always bring
to that lived experience. I don't need to
go into a lot of detail about that. The
point is it's just a very, specific word
that had deep meaning for my family.
And for him to choose that one, and I am
absolutely certain he chose that one
specifically because he wanted me to hear
him. He wanted me to know exactly what I
was seeing because Selma was just like, oh
yeah, that's a nice word. didn't, she
didn't have no reason to know that meant
what it did. And I just, felt the presence
of my parents and I knew exactly what I
was, what I was watching.
And there was no, there was no turning
back. mean, the RPM was not the model that
worked well for us in the end, but, that
was the moment and I will never regret
that
trial and error we found because it gave
me that gift. Yeah. They got, you got you
going, right? I you on the journey. Yeah.
So now I have Evan's word right here.
That's my father's handwriting. Oh, that's
awesome.
my father's handwriting that I took from a
document after he passed. And for me,
it's both of them. It's his word, but
evidence use of it. That is super cool. I
really like that. And I'm sorry, like you
said, your parents weren't able to witness
that, because it is profound. And I'm
fortunate enough that both of my parents
are
still alive. I have a 91-year-old dad.
89 year old mom, you know, who were able
to witness this with Stone. both, they've
been divorced for years, but again, you
know, I've had good relationships and have
always been super supportive, especially
grandma. And just to talk about that
moment, we were visiting, not too long
ago. They lived down in a couple of hours
away down in the Portland area. And, Stone
said, I want to say something to grandma.
I said, yeah, what do you want to say? He
said, grandma, your unconditional love for
me,
And he said, the reason, the reason I
always kept going was because of the
unconditional love you gave me. And it was
just like so sweet and special, right?
You know, and just, you know, just totally
melted her. You know, it's just, it was a
really sweet moment. well, nobody loves
your kids the way that their grandparents
do, right? Like after you, only people
are, your parents. Yeah.
Yeah. So I'm, know, like I said, we're
fortunate that we've had that and that
he's
had that relationship and that
unconditional love and, know, the
community, like
getting back to that, like you said, is so
important because the journey, like
again, when we started back when, you
know, our sons were diagnosed even, it was
pretty lonely, right? Like you didn't have
a chance to necessarily meet other
parents.
of children on the spectrum. was far and
few between. There weren't necessarily
Facebook groups or, I remember there was
like a Yahoo group or things like that. So
we had a chance to connect with someone.
It was really kind of a unique
opportunity.
But now of course, there's been this
explosion, but there's a number of, all
kinds
of groups, associations. mean, there's a
lot of different opportunities for people.
to join communities. I was wondering, can
I get your take on that? What kind of
advice would you give parents, maybe
especially our newer, on this journey as
far as
how to navigate that without becoming
overwhelmed? Because I think that's part
of
the, I think that's one of the challenges.
You feel overwhelmed already, just I
think being on the journey. How...
navigated? You know, I think that we
tend... What
you said...
really hit hits up in your urge that
you're right, we were very isolated. were
not
just isolated, but marginalized. You know,
we couldn't have a lot of the shared
experiences that our peer group did now,
you know, stones a twin. And I also had
another child, but when you're when you
want to connect, not only do you not have
the same experiences, the first day of
kindergarten, the same, you know,
You know, they're waiting at the bus stop,
all those little things. But you don't
have the energy for it. don't have the
time for it. What I do love about the fact
that it's a lot of it social media driven
now is you can enter as you are able to
enter. But what I think is the best way to
not overload is to recognize that all of
these people that are giving you their two
cents worth
are just people, you know, they're not
more qualified than you. They're certainly
not more qualified than you about your
child. But I don't know. mean, it's a good
question. And I wish I had a better answer
for you right now because I am, I'm
somebody who, you know, I'll research and
learn and listen about almost anything.
And I don't feel that I necessarily
overload because I can separate out
you know, the person from the idea they're
presenting and I could connect with an
individual even if I don't agree with
them. I actually prefer engaging on social
media because you can opt out when you
overload. There's no obligation to respond
to
message. You know, you can't necessarily
walk away from an individual human being
in
the same room, but you can just turn off
social media. You don't even have to log
in
on a given day. that. You don't have to
answer all the
things that are said to you. But there are
real relationships formed there and there
is real value because there's nobody else
out there who has the lived experience.
It's a field that is overwhelmed by people
who teach, not do. And other parents are
the people who may not be able to teach,
but they sure know how to do. And if they
don't know how to do, then...
whatever they've messed up is probably
something you're going to mess up too and
vice versa. Yeah. No, that's a really good
point. I think social media, again, I was
going to say, I think that's one of the
benefits. You know, again, we could say
it's
a double-edged sword. I've worked in the
industry. My day job, so to speak, is
doing
background PR and digital marketing as
I've been doing social media from the
early
days and I've seen the different changes.
And again, it's become a double-edged
sword, of course, with
Misinformation, disinformation, trolls,
all kinds of things. The great thing is,
you
know, some of these communities, like you
said, the one that we're, you know, that
connected us, the Spellers community and
how that's just kind of, it's blown me
away. I mean, by far, but kind of the best
online community that I've been part of.
And like you said, just the knowledge
sharing. think for me, the difference is,
especially again, going back 10 years and
when we were kind of like in that
knowledge,
seeking phase, especially it's all. There
was like, there was an opportunity to ask
a lot of questions. Like you could go to
an association or a group and you'd like
read papers or you just like, and you're
trying to make it kind of fit your
situation, right? Like, and we know that
everything is so unique that it's just
really hard. Plus it's just time
consuming. Whereas again, like you said,
here you
go into a group and just say, here's my
situation, you know, blah, What do you
guys
think?
you know, and you get kind of that instant
feedback from people in addition to the
support, right? Well, and it's okay to
prioritize the things that you already
like,
what you're hearing. It's okay to do that.
You know, when we were starting out, I
went to Autism Speaks. It was the only
thing out there. And I remember at the
time,
like I was very grateful for the...
stability that they offered as an
organization and we have the answers kind
of
thing. But anytime their advice didn't
particularly resonate with me, what other
choice did I have? I mean, there was no
place else to look. And that doesn't mean
that you decision shop. But if what you're
working on right now is a biomedical
intervention, if what you're working on
right now is letter boards, if it's any
one
of a thousand different things,
It's okay to prioritize the things that
are already working for your family and
your
values and your priority. I think that we
do, much like we put value on the spoken
word, we also put value on the written
word. Just cause you see it on the
internet
doesn't make it true. What's that like
mean going around? Like you can't, you
can't
believe everything that you see on the
internet.
and it's a quote by Abraham Lincoln.
Right, the help of that. You know, it's
like
that. But that's what the world is too,
right? Like it's not any different from
what
we're doing in our day-to-day lives in
text. You've got to filter, you've got to
prioritize and like said, you know, ask
correct questions and understand where and
who's the information coming from, what
makes them qualified, you know, like I
said,
you know, I think that's...
always helpful to try to have those
identifiers. If there's a post and when
people
are responding, hey, I'm a physician and I
can tell you XYZ versus I'm a dad and
here's my experience. You and I have kind
of offline discussion about that. It's not
even like nefarious intent necessarily,
but still I think that context is really
helpful. Well, I'll tell you what they do
all have in common though. I say this
about...
teachers too. One thing when I'm working
on an advocacy case, but I can always say
is true about teachers, special education
teachers in particular, is there's not a
one of them that entered that field
because they thought they were going to
get rich
doing it. There's not a one of them that
entered that field for the big paycheck,
the short hours, the easy work. I don't
believe you encounter anyone that is in
any
of those autism support groups for any
reason other than they just want to do the
right fitting.
by themselves, their child, their family
member, their loved one. That is the one
thing they have in common. And I think the
overwhelming majority of them would go to
war in order to pursue that outcome. That
is a baptism or a shared bondage by fire.
And somebody else's way may not be my way,
but I can absolutely respect.
that you are working all day long every
day to remove barriers for your child. And
your solution might look different from
mine, but your drive comes from the same
place. And so I honor that no matter who's
offering the solution. And in spite of
what, you know, I tell myself on the
daily, I don't know everything. And I've
come
across a lot of nuggets, a lot of nuggets
that I just never would have considered
had I not left myself open to that.
Yeah, no, that's a great point. You know,
and the other thing kind of in terms of a
segue here, it's all my 10 years ago,
something that I certainly didn't have
that I
wish we had, you know, stones wrapping up
his high school experience now,
thankfully, after, you know,
communicating, spelling, and I could be
able to
understand his capabilities that he can
handle age appropriate material. He's now
in
a private school.
Again, for those who are listening, know
my story quite yet, but again, after being
a public school, had to, we had to take
some steps, some legal steps to get there.
But, you know, like I said, this gets back
to just, again, feel like you're solo.
And I remember knowing that he needed more
support back way back when he was in
third grade. Right. And, know, you get
into this world of IEPs and, you know, the
public school district. And it's just,
again, talking about overwhelming for the
common person.
I wish I had an advocate. I wish we had
someone like you, Elizabeth. I'm so, and
I've had a chance to meet a few others,
particularly from our group who all, it's
like, is something that's needed because
it's just, like I said, so overwhelming
and
it's just the odds are really kind of
stacked against the parents, you know,
when
you're, you feel like you're going into a
knife fight with, you know, a fork maybe,
know, plastic fork at that.
I think one of the reasons that it is
overwhelming is because parents are told
that
they should be able to navigate it on
their own. And so when they can't, they
think
something's wrong. But you would never
have entered into your legal battle
without
an attorney. So did you think that you
were capable of doing that without, or you
would never have, you know, self-diagnosed
or whatever the many things are.
But we're told we should be able to do it.
We're told that the system is fair. We're
told all of these things that aren't
actually true. I do think the system tries
to
be fair, but ultimately, you are
representing your child, your heart, a
piece of
yourself, and for them it's their job. And
they may care very deeply about their
job, I don't doubt that, but not as much
as you care about your child.
I'm going to push back just a little bit
in terms of, my personal experience in
that. And again, you're talking, and I
think maybe you're talking about the
educators themselves. the- Yes, I am. Not
the system, no. I don't think the system,
I don't think the system, you know, this
has been one of my takeaways and huge
disappointments, crushing disappointment.
I've always been an advocate for public
education. My brother just retired. was a,
he was a-
a middle school and high school teacher
for a number of years. know, like it's
just,
kind of runs like, you know, runs in the
blood sort of a thing. And again, so that,
hope and expectation that yeah, okay,
yeah, they're doing the best, you know,
this
is really the best, you know, was
shattered after a couple of years. Like I
said,
once we, when we knew that he, that Stone
needed more support, deserved more
support, we even provided some examples of
how he had excelled with, you know, with
some outside.
some of the outside work that we were
doing. And just to have it shut down
multiple
times. And then I just felt helpless,
right? Like then we were like, okay, we're
just stuck in the system. We're just
stuck. So I don't think we disagree. So
when I
say they want to be fair, I think that
they have an internal narrative about what
it
is they're doing. The actual deliverable
is not necessarily fair.
I understand what you're saying and I
definitely have come across toxic people.
is
rarely ever a classroom teacher. Rarely.
mean, maybe some very outlying margins of
people have come across one or two that it
was a classroom teacher. It's usually in
the system. And I think that the problem's
bigger than education because these are
entities that survive.
with limited means and infinite need. And
part of the reason that they can get
through the day to day is through the
system of smoke and mirrors, know, barring
computer to pay Paul. know, the ones who
fall through the cracks are the ones that
are more expensive to educate and the ones
that more, that require them to step
outside of their standardized practice.
And, you know, as a society, we don't
value
public education. We like to talk about
teachers and how great they are. It will
give you your 5 discount at Starbucks. You
can show me your teacher ID, but don't
raise my taxes because that might go to
school. Don't raise my taxes. Don't do
that because that'll go to school. That's
an
issue, right? know, it's not going to get
better until the whole world recognizes
the value of, gets like stoned of it.
I hope you're enjoying the lighter side of
the spectrum. So far we're commercial
free, but if you're finding value here,
one way to support the show is by
considering me for speaking engagement. I
speak on unlocking potential, whether it's
for individuals like my son or for entire
organizations. I also offer fractional CMO
services for businesses needing strategic
marketing support without the full-time
commitment, drawing on over 35 years of
experience in marketing.
My agency has helped companies and
healthcare practices increase their value,
grow,
and even prepare for acquisition. To learn
more about my speaking topics, visit
davidkoffer.com. Or if you're interested
in our marketing or fractional CMO
services, check out kofermarketing.com. If
you're enjoying this episode, please
leave a review. Your feedback means a lot
and it helps me make this podcast even
more useful. Lastly, don't forget to share
it with anyone who would appreciate the
insights and stories we're sharing here.
Thanks again for listening.
Well, speaking of Stone, he's making an
appearance. So he likes to pop in, just
say
hi, and just let me know what he's doing.
Yeah, I almost... Before I got online, I
thought to myself, know, Evan sometimes in
the afternoon, he kind of vocalizes, he
gets a little loud. And then I thought,
you know what, I all the audiences that
I'm
going to hear. Hey, right? Like, this is
our world. I mean, this is...
And especially again, for you and I
working from home and juggling that. talk
about,
again, we haven't really talked about,
talk about like, what does it mean to be
an
advocate versus like, again, some of these
people who are facing challenges, when
might they look at talking to someone like
you, maybe that versus talking to
attorney or in addition to kind of help
provide context for people to say, you
know,
what do you do?
So there's two things that I think are the
most important skills that I have. One is
diplomacy, and that diplomacy probably
rises to the level of either Henry
Kissinger
or Madeleine Albright, depending on your
party, but a pretty extensive ability to
manage those conversations. The other
thing that I'm very good at, I think, is
translating school eaves to parry eaves
and back again.
those two languages are tricky because
they both sound like English, you know?
And I
think about the movie The Princess Bride
and where one of the characters says, you
keep using that word, that does not mean
what you think it means about, well, it's
so inconceivable is the word that, and I
keep using that word, it does not mean
what
you think it means. you know, I can
understand English and all the words
separately,
but not put together in that order. And
that is...
the source of a lot of the issues at the
IEP table. So I guess I would say that the
time to engage in advocate is when you
feel that the tide is rising beyond your
capacity to understand. And I know that
can happen very early and not everybody
has
the means to do it. I come to this work,
it's a second career for me.
It's the one I should have had all along
and I love it. I'm driven by it every day.
People think I'm crazy, but A, know,
somebody, has to love it, right? That
happens
to be me. I think that, because I come to
this as a parent, you know, I give a lot
of information away for free. lot of it
for free. I'll vouch for that. I'm happy
to
do that because partly because it's the
person I want to be.
But also because I know I approach, I've
been independently employed for my whole
adult life, really 30 plus years in
another field before this. And, you know,
I have
always held by the standard that yes,
information is power, but that power is
magnified when that information is freely
shared. I don't lessen my value by giving
you what I know. What I do is I increase
my value because I have
position myself as the expert and the
source. That doesn't mean I give away all
my
tricks to the trait, but I don't want
parents to feel inhibited by, oh, I have
to
pay her for every five minutes of
information that she gives. Quite the
opposite. I
learned a lot of what I know from parents
who were willing to share a few minutes
and answer some questions for me. And I
just don't want to look back on my life
and
say I didn't do that for others.
What's been, I'm kind of curious, as you
talk about that, what's been like one of
the biggest surprises in terms of, as
you've kind of thrown yourself into this
level
of work for you? have there been any like,
aha moments that have surprised you about
being an advocate or what family, you
know, families are going through? My say,
well, that part, what family are you going
through? because that's how I Because
you've lived it, right? Yeah.
Yeah, when my son, my older son had an IEP
when he was four, not for autism, but he
had an IEP. And I remember at the time
thinking, you know, I have legal training.
was a stay at home mom. had resources in
every way you could define those
resources.
And I struggled. And I remember at the
time thinking, if I'm struggling, what's
happening to the other kids? You're
bringing less to the table than I am. And
the
answer is they were getting lost.
What the parent experiences is not a
surprise for me. And I think it's what
part of
what makes me good at what I do is because
I know what it's like to be sitting at
that table, parsing out every deficit your
child has. I hate that word deficit, but
parsing out every bit of it and just
feeling like, I think what has surprised
me is
the ability of people to deny the obvious.
to just being able to completely disregard
the pink elephant in the room and just be
able to, and I believe they really,
they're not faking it. They really have
built up
this cognitive dissonance around, no,
that's just not true. That's just not
true.
That's just not. It's not true, it's not
possible, right? And how, in some of these
cases,
People can look in the mirror and tell
themselves that they're actually doing
right
by a child with a disability. I mean,
think about that for a minute. You know,
you're choosing to be right, your
interpretation of right, okay? So I'm not
actually
saying that there's a black and white,
you're the good guy, you're the bad guy.
I'm
not saying that at all. But what you think
is right is happening at the expense of
a...
child with a disability. Meanwhile, you're
presumably able-bodied in a position of
power. And you can choose between being
right or being happy. You choose to be
right
at expense of this person that you are
charged with their care and their
education.
I don't know how people build that sky of
a barrier in their mind that they can't
see.
I don't know either. don't, yeah, it's
hard. It's, impossible to understand,
right?
Cause again, it's never been there and
again, can't imagine going there, but like
you said, it just, it just has never
really made sense other than, guess you
just, I
don't know, you just have to convince
yourself somehow that's that, you're doing
the
right thing. And this, you know, this is
especially true, you know, in terms of
that.
just that bewilderment that I've had with
the system. So there's one thing, like
said, know that Stone was going through
the school system before he could
communicate. And like you, Elizabeth, I
knew that he was in there. I knew that,
right? And like you, was just like, gotta
unlock that key. I just gotta find that
key, whatever that is. We're gonna find
that and we're gonna get him up. In the
meantime, it's like I still...
wanted him to get an education. And then
as he got shoehorned into this kind of
intensive ed, the work experience program,
it was just heartbreaking to see that.
But again, it felt kind of powerless. But
then once he, again, attained the
communication and we just said, we just
want him to get access to education that
he
deserves. And to have that just like
turned down and just, you know, just
Like, no, he's not capable. just like, why
are you in this job? Like, what are you
talking about? And just that they were
just so close-minded to even the
possibility
that he had the capability, even though,
we went through all the different
assessments and things like that. And that
just kind of blew me away. Yeah, you've
heard me say online, and I wish I could
just...
put it in people's minds before they go
too far down, a whole... Minds don't
change
with evidence. They just don't. Because
once you've made up your mind, evidence
isn't going to be the thing that changes
it. It's not how human beings are wired.
Minds change with emotion. I will also
say, I wish I had known that myself a long
time ago, because I was given so much bad
advice in the beginning. So much bad
advice. I mean...
I look back now and the advice, the best
advice available was bad advice. But I
had-
That's bad and that's bad. Yeah. I had a
Yale educated pediatrician tell me when I
informed her that we have received an
autism diagnosis, she said to me, well,
you
know, just because he's autistic now
doesn't mean he always will be. That was
one,
that was one of the single worst pieces of
advice I ever got.
And the best advice I would, I could have
received would have been, well, you know,
he's the same kid before you had that word
that he is today. He didn't change. He
just have a name for it. That would have
been good advice. Now people say that now
they didn't say that back then. And, I
still resent that now, you know, through
the
eyes of a trained advocate. Now, what I,
what I know, what she meant was.
as young as he was potentially, know,
developmental milestones are very highly
variable. You know, it didn't mean that he
was always going to present the way that
he presented that day. But to say it the
way she did and to imply that was the gold
standard, that he'd be non-autistic was so
offensive and so wrong and just not what
I needed or any parent needs to hear. No.
No, that's so true. And like you said,
yeah, I mean, you bring back memories.
Yeah,
I do. Don't I? We're getting all twitchy
because we're triggers. Yeah. mean, part
of
this, you know, is it's survival, right?
Like you're, I didn't have, you know, over
the last, you know, but now since the
diagnosis, how much of this time maybe you
felt like you were in survival mode? I'll
let you know when it ends. Yeah.
Because the threat is constant. The threat
is, first it was, I mean, now I know I'm
biased, okay, but my son was a very cute
little kid, very cute little kid. And the
world would forgive him of a host of
challenges that he presented. But now he's
a
hairy adult male and they're not as
forgiving. And when I think of students
that are
students of color,
on top of them presenting differently and
the risks the world presents to them. We
live in a very judgmental world. It's
becoming more so in the last six to eight
years as we've had people give voice to
divisive language that validates
discrimination. Yeah. That validate the
ugly things people feel inside. And it's
all
very fear-based and lowest common
denominator of our
of our experience as human beings. But I
lived that every day and, you know, the,
stress hormone that, what is the stress
hormone? The, cortisol in your mind, in
your
brain, I'm totally sure that my, cortisol
level, my baseline is other people's
stress level. Cause that's just what we
live. And it, it's because I'm here to
be protective of him and the world is a
constant threat to him. Yeah. That's just
the reality. Yeah. And I think again,
that's been kind of, you know, I'm talking
about what, you know, presenting and a lot
of the show, you know, talking about the
lighter side of autism, right? But that,
you know, it's not all light, right? There
is, there are some dark days, there are
challenges that, we face that they face
that
I think, you know, we have to acknowledge.
And I think, like you said, it's kind of
interesting how it, I don't know, for me,
it feels like sometimes they just kind of
come in waves too, right? Like you said,
there was the, just the incredible joy and
excitement that came with spelling and
the communication and all that that's
opened up, which has been incredible. But
then
like, you know, kind of once you get past
that, the storming, the forming, right?
But then all of a sudden it's kind of like
this reality of like,
Oh shit. Like I've got this like
incredible 18 year old guy here who, you
know,
deserves an education. Like all this stuff
has all these capabilities, all these
needs. You know, now what? Like again,
there's still no, there's no roadmap for
this. Like there's no guide. Like we're,
here we go. We, got to figure out how to
do
this, how to get the degree, how to get
them to college. And I know there are
others
who have done it, but it's just kind of
like this other, it's like, oh, there's
another, mountain in front of us now, that
we kind of got through that.
I think once I got past the many lies the
world was telling me about autism, it gave
me permission to question more
assumptions. And what that meant for us
was education
doesn't have to look the way that the
public school system says it has to look.
He
doesn't have to finish at a time. That's a
great point. Yeah, it doesn't have to
finish at a time that the...
public education system says most kids are
going to be done. We can write our own
ticket. And, you know, I would not wish
for, I don't think any parent would wish
for
their child to enter into a world that
isn't built for them. And that would
constantly challenge that. But I am so
grateful, so eternally grateful every hour
of
every day of my life for, you know, the
opportunity
to refine life skills that he has needed
me to refine. it's not about me, it's not,
autism is my story, but parenting somebody
and loving somebody the way that I love
my child and knowing that the world isn't
built for him, that is my story. And I'm
just so grateful I'm a better person for
what he needed from me. And I...
pity the people that don't witness the
gifts that I get to witness and that you
get
to witness. What a gift. To get a peek
into these beautiful minds. know? Oh,
that's
a whole, that's a whole, that's a whole
nother conversation we could have later.
Right? Because it, truly is. And it's,
yeah, it's a gift. It's fascinating. It's
like I said, exciting. It's, you know,
there's so many words to use. It is a gift
though.
And just to be said to me, but I was just
going to back up with something you said,
because I think it's a really important
point for people. And again, especially if
you're again, early on with their journey,
if you have, know, yeah, first, second,
third grade or whatever it may be. Like
you said, don't be afraid to write the
rules. mean, again, I think we get,
especially again, in my case, again, you
feel
like you have to be on this track and
And there are so many more options. know,
part of it, are more options now, but
again, open your mind to these options,
whatever, you know, whatever it be. That
doesn't mean go chasing down fool's gold
or whatever, but when it comes to
education, really try to explore, like you
said, could be, the path can be very
different. It could look however you want.
And that's, something I wish we would
have done or could have done at an earlier
age for, students. Yeah. People, say to
me in my practice,
Things like, well, you know, what's he
supposed to know by third grade? And
obviously, you know, grade levels are just
stories made up by people sitting in a
room in state cap, right? You know that,
right? Like there has to be
standardization, of course, and there has
to be some data by which we can measure
things. you know, human beings aren't
easily measured in two dimensional terms.
And
so, you know, I always say let go of what
the academic benchmarks.
are supposed to be, because that's an
illusion, right? But do not let go of the
demand that your child still deserves to
love learning. you can miss a day, week, a
month, a year of school. You will catch up
if you love it, but you will never come
back if your spirit is broken around the
idea of learning, being a lifelong
learner.
You know, learning didn't begin when you
started school. didn't end when you left
school. Who among us are in the career
that they studied for? You know, our local
superintendent of schools here says
something like 75 of kids in high school
today
will have jobs that don't exist yet. you
know, so really what we're teaching them
is
how to think. I have never used geometry
after high school. I have never used out.
I
mean, maybe I've used some algebra.
But my point is I never, I never stopped
loving the process of learning. That's
what
I want to protect in all the kids I work
with. Least of all my own, know? And given
the opportunity in some cases, right? Like
I said, we know that, you know, there are
some, bad situations where they're not
learning anything. They really are just
kind
of segregated into these kinds of special
ed classrooms where there's very little
instruction and it's more. Yeah.
caretaking almost rather than educational
focused. It's funny, you mentioned
geometry, Elizabeth. And so actually
that's one of the classes Stone's taking.
And
just, think it was last week or so, you
know, the teacher said, hey Stone, do you
have any questions? And he said yes. And
she's like, yeah, what's that? He said,
how
am I going to use this in life? Right. The
age-old question. I can answer that.
Assembling IKEA furniture. Oh, there you
go.
But other than that, no. And if he's never
going to assemble IKEA furniture and
every college student has to assemble IKEA
furniture sooner or later, you know, I
have heard that part of why a lot of
autistic students love math so much is
because
there's rules and there's, it's clearly
stated to them. This is what you do. This
is
how you do it kind of thing. I suppose
there's organic pieces of geometry that
unbeknownst to myself, I have used in my
life.
but Evan, man, he just can't get enough of
math. In spite of that, I'm quite sure he
is actually my child, but he did not come
by his love of math genetically. can, I
can swear by that. Yeah. But he loves it.
Good for him. And we all need something to
love, right? Like I'm happy it makes him
happy, but me personally, I don't see the
use. Who knows though? Maybe he's going to
launch a rocket in his life one day.
Maybe he's going to, who knows?
Who knows? mean, again, right? I mean,
it's not so far fetched to say, again,
I'll
only speak for myself that, you know,
again, I didn't think this day was going
to be
possible. I didn't think that there would
be the time that Stone would be where he
is, you know, communicating, taking
classes with, know, so much potential,
opportunity, real opportunity in front of
him. You know, this has just been a, so.
That has really inspired me again, just
kind of in life in general, have a good
reminder. we just, we don't know what's
possible. I mean, it's a cliche, but it's
so
true. So who knows? Like you said, what
kind of conversation are we going to be
having in five years about Evan? Yeah.
know, like. mean, my goal really is just
that
he's satisfied with the choices. I mean, I
was raised by parents, more my mom, but
by parents who used to say to me,
Look, if you decide that you want to sweep
floors for a living, I will buy you the
best room and I will send you to the best
floor sweeping school that there is. I
just don't want you to be left with that
as the only choice you have because of
arbitrary barriers in your world. And
that's what I want for him. mean, there's,
you
know, even if he got, you know, all of the
education available, he still has other
very practical realities about navigating
his world.
I just see my role as a presumed
neurotypical or neuro-dominant. I like to
call
myself neuro-fierce. I like that. Neuro-
fierce-ity. But I'll be the one to get the
barriers out of the way for him and then
he gets to choose his path. If he decides
that just during geometry exercises for
the rest of his life or who knows? I just
don't want him to be left with that.
That the only choice he has. I want it to
be an active decision on his part. And so
many people in the world, autistic or not,
don't have that luxury. If I can give
that to him, the luxury of choice, my work
here is done. So what in kind of, in
closing, like I said, as, we predicted, we
could talk forever. You know, and like,
definitely want to have you on to another
segment. There's a couple of things didn't
get to, that I think would be great
topics, but in closing here, one of the
things I
was
curious is what gives you excitement, what
makes you excited about the future? I
think we just talked about it,
opportunity. look back at what we've
talked about
actually a number of times just in this
conversation. I look back at what the
world
looked like when I first entered the
experience that is parenting an autistic
child.
And that wasn't that long ago in the terms
of human change. It was, you know,
15, 16 years ago for us. What's it going
to look like in another 15, 16 years?
Because I look at the enormity of that
change and it's picking up speed. It's
happening faster now. So if it were on a
timeline and we'd come this far in that
period, we're going to go much, further
than that in the next same time period.
And
I'm just grateful to sit back and bask in
their reflected glory as they take on the
world.
We're already seeing trends in workplaces
where they actually seek out employees
that think like our kids do. That's just
growing the seeds of change. Look at what
the internet has done in the time we've
witnessed it. Though that's what excites
me
is the world is waking up. Maybe not as
fast as I hoped for, but a lot faster than
I
thought would happen if I had to predict
It seems to be accelerating fairly
quickly.
And again, but maybe that's just a
personal bias, again, based on my
awareness. But
it does, you know, again, it does feel
like, it feels like this is really, you
know,
something that's getting some momentum,
some real momentum, like you said. I think
it is. And I think that that's the way all
change has occurred over history. Good
point. You know, there's books written
about it, about critical mass. And, you
know,
that's what I think we're written as that.
You don't ever know at what point it
happened until you're looking back on it,
but
it feels that way. does. It does. Yeah.
I've been fortunate enough to, you know,
in
my career work in the tech industry and
then kind of pre and early internet days,
you know, a startup and like, it's, really
kind of funny that it has a similar vibe
right now. Kind of, especially again in
our
in our community of the non-speaking world
and the communicate, the spellers,
typers, whatever you want to call them.
And it's this growth that we're seeing and
this knowledge sharing. it's just like, it
really is exciting. That's what I'm
jazzed about. And I didn't work in the
tech industry, but I was always an early
adopter. was in the early days of Usenet
and constant. I was always an early
adopter.
I witnessed what you're talking about, you
know, from the outside as a user. so,
yeah, I mean, I would liken where we are
right now to when, you know, for example,
AOL was huge and everybody was using AOL
and eventually that outlived its purpose.
at that point, you know, we, the animals
have left the barnyard at that point. So,
you know, I feel like we're in this, phase
where, you know, you tell two people and
they tell two people and you tell two
people.
Sooner or later, you know, the community
is going to outgrow the box that it
started
in and it's going to have to find a bigger
box or no box at all. But yeah, it's,
feel it too. So maybe I'm as biased as you
are, but. Oh, we're kind of in the
tornado to use that, you know, that old,
that old analogy. remember there's
something inside the tornado, right? Those
are the tech books. Well.
Gosh, Elizabeth, thank you so much. mean,
first of all, thanks for being on the
podcast. Also, thanks for what do for the
community, all the support and advice
you've given me. We're definitely going to
have to pick this up and do a part two
down the road because there's so much more
to talk about. So thank you. Well, thank
you for having me and thank you for what
you're doing to continue to be an advocate
for this community.
this podcast and in many other ways,
you're a relative newcomer to it, as
opposed to
me being the OG. But I just so appreciate
people lending their intelligence and
gifts and connections and resources to
expanding the methods. You talked about
the
reference to J.D. Hanley and you know,
back when he was starting, I just happened
to
be one of the people he picked up the
phone and talked to early on and, you
know,
Every little bit, every person talking
about it, you never know when that right
person is going to hear something that's
going to have some other gift to add to
the
community. So I'm grateful for you pushing
that ball down the field a little bit
further too. Well, thank you. And that's,
precisely my goal. Like if it's one person
who hears this that again, that it helps
them and gets them on the path, you know,
it's, worth it because we know, we know
the trade-offs. So, and if you're
listening,
thanks for sticking with us through this.
Hopefully you got a lot out of it.
Feel free to give me feedback. My website
is davidkoffert.com. Share this podcast
with others who may find it interesting
and you can subscribe at all the usual
suspects. So for now, we'll catch you next
time on the lighter side of the spectrum.